Welcome back, everybody.
This week, we get to talk about what is called
higher-order functions.
And when we say higher-order functions, then
probably there is also something else like
a lower-order function; but actually, they
are not called lower-order functions, but
rather first-order functions.
And almost everything you have seen so far
of Haskell, and certainly everything you have
written yourself in Haskell (unless you have
somehow done something in addition to this
lecture), have been first-order functions.
Now, higher-order functions are a very essential
ingredient of the functional programming paradigm.
Actually, if we had only first-order functions,
then the paradigm wouldn't be so interesting.
Higher-order functions are what basically
gets us from programming *of* functions to
actually programming *with* functions and
programming *on* functions, so, dealing with
functions themselves as ingredients, in a
sense, as data on which we can program further
functions.
So, that is what higher-order is about.
And you have already seen a few higher-order
functions, maybe without explicitly noticing
it.
Because you didn't have to do anything with
them other than simply leave them as they
were given in the task templates.
Here I will briefly remind you of these instances.
And then we will look at a few, probably,
somewhat bizarre looking examples first.
Also, there is certain new syntax that becomes
important when we want to program with higher-order
functions.
So, I have to introduce *this*.
And some of this will maybe look very strange
at the beginning.
And then we will come back again to more useful
cases, so, some things that you will actually
use in the exercises, or that are generally
important for programming in Haskell.
As I have just said, so far, we have mainly
dealt with first-order functions.
So, functions that take normal data as input
arguments and ultimately return something
which is also normal data.
By "normal data" we mean things like lists,
numbers, pairs, pairs of numbers, lists of
numbers, lists of pairs, etc.
It is concrete data that you can print and
pass to another function, and the output may
be also printed.
So, if you think of functions that you have
seen, actually the 'reverse' function:
You give it a list, it gives back a list.
That is a typical first-order function.
Or, the addition of numbers is a first-order
function:
You give it two numbers, it gives you back
a number.
That's first-order, normal data.
In a few occasions, we have actually at least
got in touch already with higher-order
functions, namely 'quickCheck' and 'animationOf'.
So, if you think about 'quickCheck' as the
driver of this testing approach, and 'animationOf'
as one of the main drivers of the CodeWorld
approach (of this small language for describing
animations), these two are higher-order functions.
Because we passed other functions to them.
In the case of quickCheck, we didn't call
this out very explicitly.
But actually, what we gave to 'quickCheck'
were functions.
So, I mentioned that I give a property to
quickCheck: something like expressing that
whenever we have two lists, then the length
of their concatenation is the same as the
sum of the lengths.
That is something like "for all xs, for all
ys, the following condition holds".
Well, this is really a predicate.
It is a function.
You give it normal data values like lists,
and it gives you a Boolean value (True or
False).
So, it's a predicate.
And a predicate is a function from some domain
to True and False (the Bool type).
And 'quickCheck' took such a predicate as an
argument.
So, if 'quickCheck' is seen as a function, which
it should be because what we are using here
from the QuickCheck library is a function;
you give it a predicate, and it does something
with it.
It is a function to which you give another
function (a predicate) as argument.
And similarly for 'animationOf'
If you remember: First, in CodeWorld, we programmed
Pictures.
So, then we had something like simply a Picture,
that is first-order data.
The first scene calls were using 'drawingOf'.
And to 'drawingOf' you gave a Picture and
then it did something with it, namely, put
it on the screen.
For 'animationOf' we did something else.
We had to program a function.
And what did we do with this function?
We gave it to 'animationOf'.
So, we had something like "main = animationOf
scene" (as an argument, the 'scene' function).
So, we had animations, functions from "time"
to 'Picture'.
And then we gave such a function to 'animationOf'.
So, 'animationOf' again was a function.
It took an argument which itself was a function.
This is the contrast here between 'animationOf'
and 'drawingOf', for example, or 'quickCheck'
and other functions that we have seen.
So, let's indeed look at the type of 'animationOf'.
We could make a similar observation for 'quickCheck',
but let's do it on 'animationOf'.
What do we have here?
So, this is the type.
I have never really shown that type in the
lecture, and partly because you might have
been surprised at that point because we didn't
have the concepts for talking about this.
But actually, if we do give the type, then
unlike 'drawingOf', where we would simply
have "the argument as a Picture, and the outcome
is: do something interactive, in this case,
drawing it to the browser window", now "animationOf"
gets a function as argument.
So, what we are saying here is: the first
argument of 'animationOf' is itself a function
from Double to Picture, and then there is
some output.
The latter is the interactive aspect.
But the interesting bit is this part here,
and in particular, that there are these brackets.
This is important here, to indicate that this
whole part here constitutes the input, namely
the *input* is a function from Double to Picture;
and not that 'animationOf' is a function somehow
of two arguments: Double and Picture, and
then something comes out.
That would be a wrong way of reading it.
So, these brackets here are really important.
And we will come back to this syntax difference
and its importance.
An important note here: Every function is
a value, of course.
So, usually, you think about functions as
taking values as arguments.
And once you realize that a function is itself
also a value (mathematically), there is no
real surprise, maybe, that a function can
take another function as an argument.
That may be a surprise only because in programming,
we often cannot do this so simply.
But mathematically, if we accept (and we should)
that every function is also a value, then
clearly, functions that can take values as
arguments should also be allowed to take functions
as arguments (if the type allows this, like
in this case).
Conversely, not every value is a function.
We have values in Haskell, like values of
type Double, to which you cannot pass an argument.
So, Double itself is not a function.
"Double → Picture" is a function.
And to this function you can give an argument,
like the time Double value 3.5.
But a value of type Double is of course not
a function, so you cannot give an argument
to it.
That is a really important observation and
thing to keep in mind:
Every function is a value, of course, mathematically
speaking, and that's then embodied here in
how we can program with these entities. But
not every value is a function.
So, saying something like: "Haskell is a functional
language. So, everything in Haskell is a function."
... that wouldn't be true.
So, we have to be careful of this.
Also, maybe when I talked about 'quickCheck'
here, I almost stumbled about this.
Of course, we also have things that are not
functions.
So, here is the type, again, of 'animationOf'.
And here more explicitly what I already said
on the previous slide.
These brackets here are very important because
without them, the type would mean something
completely different.
Remember that on the expression level, basically
for data, for expressions, for values, we
(and also Autotool) somehow pushed you into
the direction of using fewer brackets.
There were all of these warnings/suggestions
like:
"You don't need brackets here, write it more
simply with fewer brackets."
On the type level, for example between this
type and this type, you will not get these
kinds of warnings because it would be completely
wrong.
These mean completely different things.
This is a thing which takes a function as
an argument and then something happens.
And this type here says: We have a function
to which we give two normal values (two non-function
values), namely a 'Double' (a number) and a
'Picture', and then something is drawn, for
example.
So, with this 'animationOf' version in the
second line here, you could only provide a
number and a fixed Picture.
That wouldn't be the basis for an actual animation.
For that, we need a function.
And the brackets here explain/indicate this.
So, these brackets here are very significant
and can't be omitted.
And to drive home this point, I will discuss
this on a simpler example where we don't have
this strange 'IO' here, which maybe also confuses
you.
So, I will make an example where we have just
numbers, but the same kind of difference between
something like this and something like this
will appear.
So, this is the example that I want to use
for this discussion: a simple function you
have seen many times before.
So, from the syntax perspective, a function
which takes two arguments.
And we know that that's how this is written:
'Int' to 'Int' to 'Int'.
Two inputs which are integers and an output
which is also an integer.
Now you can ask yourself: What are some functions
of that type?
And I'm sure you can immediately have some
ideas of functions that you could, right now,
program in Haskell and they have this type.
Something like adding two numbers or any kind
of other arithmetic combination of two inputs,
x and y, for example.
In contrast, we have this type where we added
these brackets, which, we now know, mean that
this part here means we have a function as
an argument instead of two numbers as arguments.
And then, to think about what kind of things
"live" in this type, so what kind of things
that you can write in Haskell would have this
type, as a whole (not only the input type,
but the type of this 'f' as a whole).
What could 'f' actually be?
There are two things we have to wonder about:
What kind of inputs?
What can we give to this 'f'? And we know this:
two numbers.
And what kind of inputs can we give to this
'f'?
And intuitively, we know: well, functions from
integers to integers.
Not two arguments, but instead here one is
input and one is output.
And then, what can these functions do with
their inputs?
For this type, we know what this function
can do with its numbers.
It can look at them, add them, subtract them,
multiply them, do more complicated computations,
for example.
What about this function?
Knowing that it takes a function as an argument
is nice.
But now, what does it do with that argument?
That's the question here.
And we have to decide, or actually the language
design decides what 'f' can do with the argument.
There are different choices.
For example, we could imagine:
Maybe if we give to this 'f' a function, then
maybe 'f' can take this function, look at its
function definition, and work with the syntax,
with the body of that function definition,
for example.
Should this be allowed or not?
So, what can 'f' do?
That's something we need to discuss in order
to get a good grasp of what really happens in
such a higher-order function, or what makes
a higher-order function.
So, let's do this with these two simple functions.
And the main point is about the second one,
of course.
The first one is just a standard function
kind, of which you have already seen examples.
So, let's consider this first example: functions
of this simple first-order type.
What could be such functions?
And I have already mentioned some.
So, for example, the function which takes two
arguments x and y (and we know the syntax
for a two-argument function) and then the
output could be x + y, or of course, f x y
= x – y.
Or maybe 'f' ignores the first argument and
simply returns the second one.
Or maybe 'f' will even ignore both arguments
and return 12 or some other thing.
We could write more complex expressions on
the right-hand side.
So, these are functions of this type.
And I don't mean one function with these four
definitions, but basically one of them.
So, 'f' :: ... and the first one or second one
or the third one or the fourth one, each of
these lines, together with the signature above,
would give a reasonable function of that type
we see here.
Let's look in contrast at functions of the
other type, which was written like this, with
these extra brackets.
And I have already indicated or tried to explain
why they are important.
And now we see this in more detail.
So, what would this be?
So, it's a function.
It has to take an argument.
What would be its argument?
The argument is only one, namely the thing
that is written in brackets above.
It takes as argument a function.
So, let's maybe not call this x.
Let's call this g or h, which sounds more
like a function.
So, this takes only one argument, which is
a function.
Let's call it h.
And then it has to return something.
What does it have to return?
An integer.
Because that is what appears on the right-hand
side of the outer function arrow above.
So, what could it return?
Well, maybe let's use the 'h' somehow.
We have a function from 'Int' to 'Int', and we
should give back an 'Int'.
What could we do?
Well, we could take this 'h' and apply it to
7.
Yes, 'h' is a function from 'Int' to 'Int'.
We give it an 'Int', it returns an 'Int', whatever
h of 7 is.
And that's the outcome of our f-function,
given the h-function as an input.
That would be *a* reasonable definition.
Or something else.
Again, I will write down several lines, and
each of them itself is a reasonable definition
of 'f' with the type above.
So, for example, we could also decide to ignore
the function argument (the argument which
is a function) here, and just like on the
left-hand side, return 12 or 17, or whatever.
That would be a reasonable function f.
What else could 'f' do with its input?
The input is a function h.
What could 'f' do with a function 'h' (from 'Int'
to 'Int')?
Of course, it could apply it to other things
than 7 above.
But there are more things that it could do.
For example, it could apply this h-function
to the result of 'h' applied to 13, h (h 13),
or other combinations.
Or it could decide to call 'h' once on 4,
h 4, and add this together with the result of
'h' on 7, h 7.
Or, again, very many further possibilities.
So, again, this is meant as an "or", many
lines that would be possible.
And completely different lines on the left
and on the right, of course.
That's the important point.
So, on the left we have a function which takes
two numbers as arguments and then does something
with these numbers (and you know many things
that you could do with numbers), while on
the right we have a function which takes a
function as argument.
And then there are fewer things that you can
do with this, but still quite a few.
So, you cannot add 'h' to 'h', for example.
Since 'h' is a function.
You cannot add two functions.
But you can apply 'h' to something, then you
get a number.
And with this number, you can continue computing,
like outputting it directly, passing it again
to h, combining it with other values that
come out of h, for other inputs, etc.
What we see on the right here, we call this
extensional uses of this function.
That is a notion from mathematics: function
extensionality.
What this means is that we are not looking
at the syntax of h.
(I don't know why this above was somehow struck
through.)
So, what I mean here: pure extensional uses.
We are not looking at the syntax of h.
So, 'f' gets 'h' as an argument.
It can work with it.
It can apply it to numbers, work with the
results, etc.
But 'f' cannot, for example, look into the syntax
of 'h' and say:
"Oh, you are function from 'Int' to 'Int'. Let
me look whether you do this by case distinction,
or whether you are a constant function."
Or something like that.
That's not what a function can do with an
argument which is a function.
We have pure extensional uses.
And that means using the argument, in this
case h, as a mathematical function: applying
it to values and getting other values out.
Then, a reasonable question at this point
is:
Where do we get those functions from, that
we can pass as arguments to higher-order functions?
In the previous slide, where do we get the
h from that we pass to f?
I showed you 'f' of 'h' is something, some definitions.
But if I want to call the function f, I must
give it some argument, which should be a function.
Where do I get those functions from?
That shouldn't be a problem, right?
Functions are almost everywhere in Haskell.
There shouldn't be any shortage of supply.
We have plenty of functions around.
We simply have to choose some that we consider
useful to be passed as argument to f.
So, of course, we could take any predefined
function.
They have names, so they can be used as arguments.
We can refer to them by their name and then
pass them as argument to f.
In the previous example, if we take some predefined
functions from 'Int' to 'Int'.
We could use functions that we have explicitly
defined in our own program.
That is exactly what you did when you passed
your own 'scene' function, that you programmed,
as an argument to 'animationOf'.
The 'animationOf' expects a function.
You have written a function 'scene'.
So, you pass one to the other.
And, an important example way of producing,
or having, functions are partial applications
of any of the above kinds of functions (predefined
functions, own functions).
Once we have a function with two arguments,
we can also make a function with one argument.
There is a simple example here, and I will
briefly discuss this on the next slide.
But, for example, plus (+) in Haskell is a
function from two integers ('Int') to one 'Int'.
And if you pass one 'Int' to the 'plus' function,
then what you get is a function from one 'Int'
to one 'Int'.
We have already discussed this bit when I
talked about eta-reduction in one of the previous
videos, where I talked also about why the
Haskell function syntax is like it is.
In particular, it is like this to allow partial
application.
That is: If I have a two-argument function,
I can make a one-argument function from it
by providing the first argument.
On the previous slide, we had this f, and
it took an "Int to Int" as an argument.
It could, for example, take the "(+) 5" as
an argument.
That is useful.
Of course, it depends on what we want to do,
but the point is we have the possibility to
make a function from 'Int' to 'Int' by taking
a function which takes two integer arguments
and providing one of them.
And these partial applications we see here,
they have all the rights of any other function
or value in Haskell.
So, they can be passed as an argument to some
other function.
They can be stored in a data structure, for
example.
So, let us see and let's use, from the slide
before, the function "f h" is "h is applied to
7", I think.
So, that was one of these functions "from
'Int' to 'Int', as a function, goes to 'Int'".
And let's call this 'f' on one of these partial
applications.
It was written like this: plus is a binary
operation (+) which takes two numbers, we
give it one number, then we have a function
from 'Int' to 'Int'.
And this function, we give to f.
So, what does this mean?
Well, then this is h, and the right-hand side
of 'f h = h 7' means, so this above says, that
we will have 'h' applied to 7.
Which means: the plus function (+) applied
to 5, because this is h, and then applied
to 7, which is simply 12.
Right, the plus function (+) applied to 5
and 7, which is 12.
So, we simply use 'h' as an argument, and place
it wherever it needs to be.
It needs to be the function to which we pass
7 as argument.
So, then we have "h 7" is "(+) 5 of 7", (+)
5 7, which is 12.
And on the next slide, I think, we will also
see another syntax quirk.
So, actually, this "(+) applied to 5" can
also be written in a different way.
Equivalently, we can write something like
this.
This is called a section.
So, this strange incomplete-looking addition
here, this also could be 'h'.
It is the same as above, just a different
syntax.
Then it becomes even more obvious what is
happening here, in some sense.
So, then what we have, again, f h is something.
What is 'f' of 'h'?
It is 'h' of 7.
So, it is this 'h' here applied to 7.
So, it is this incomplete-looking (5 +), which
is 'h', applied to 7.
And then we, even more directly, see 5 + 7,
which is 12.
And again, this 'h' is used extensionally, here.
So, it is not like that the f function looks
at its argument and sees how it is written,
what it is doing.
No, it is simply saying: f h is h 7.
So, it uses the 'h' extensionally as a function.
And all we can really do is to pass some argument
to it; in this case, 7.
(I keep getting these strange changes to what
I have written. I don't know why this is happening,
actually. Apparently, I am not yet very firm
in this new note-taking thing here.)
So, 'h' is used purely extensionally.
Which means all you can do with the function,
really, apart from storing it in data structures,
passing it around, is to apply it to some
argument.
Which happens here with the h, when it is
applied to 7.
One way to
get a better grasp of this partial application
business is probably to realize that, actually,
the type 'Int' to 'Int' to 'Int' ("Int → Int → Int"),
that would also be the type of the plus operator
(+), can also be read as: 'Int' → ('Int' → 'Int'),
that is: 'Int' to a bracket that contains 'Int'
to 'Int'.
We just discussed this difference for the
f function between having brackets around
this part or not.
Now I am saying, the case where we don't have
brackets around this first arrow here is equivalent
or could be read as this one where we add
brackets around here.
And indeed, these brackets can be omitted.
So, this is, again, where we would say: don't
write these brackets, because it is clear
enough that this is a function of two arguments
which returns an integer.
We could also see it as this.
And then what we are actually seeing it as,
is that this is a function which takes one
number and gives back a function from 'Int'
to 'Int'.
So, this is the viewpoint of partial application.
On one hand, a function (in this viewpoint)
which takes two integers and returns one integer.
Or, from the second perspective: a function
that takes one integer and returns a function,
which is a function (in this case) that takes
one integer, namely this one, and returns
one integer.
That is just a viewpoint question between
this and this syntax.
But they are the same, mathematically.
Having a function which takes two numbers
and gives a number is the same as having a
function which takes a number and returns
a function which waits for another number
and then gives back the result.
This is, again, something that I discussed
when I discussed the eta-reduction on the
example of the opening rectangle before.
So, both of these viewpoints are valid.
There is no difference in usage, whether we
consider one or the other perspective.
And this is thanks to Haskell' function application
syntax, and also the reason why Haskell function
definitions are with this syntax, without
commas and brackets (but rather with basically
just space as function application).
So, to make these two viewpoints equivalent.
Because mathematically, they are equivalent.
This also means that, in some sense, many
first-order functions can also be seen as
higher-order functions.
We could even say: this first-order function,
the addition, is in some sense also higher-order,
because it also operates on functions.
Namely, it can be seen as taking a number
and giving back a function.
So, it doesn't take a function as argument,
but it has a function as a result.
But usually, we don't call a function like
this higher-order.
Usually, with "higher-order" we say that one
of the arguments is a function.
And, of course, this also fits with our narrative
that all functions are values.
A function is something which takes something
and gives back a value.
And this value can be a function, like in
this case.
And then, this other syntactic speciality that
I already briefly used on the previous slide,
are the so-called "sections".
I did that on this example:
If we have a binary operator which is written
like this as a function, and then we provide
one argument, like the 5, then we can also
write it as basically: "I am an operator application
where there is still missing one argument".
So, the first one is already there, but the
second part of "+" is still missing.
And I will, again, discuss this on the next
slide with a few notes.
So, let's briefly talk about operator syntax.
Probably I have to do this first.
Known from other languages is that there are
prefix and infix operators.
And in Haskell there is a special syntax for
writing an infix operator as prefix, and the
other way around.
What I did on one of the previous slides was
to write something like (+), and then I could
apply it to arguments like 5 and 7.
So, this is prefix, because it comes before
the arguments.
And of course, also the usual functions like
the 'mod' function, or f, or "rectangle",
or typical functions that you have already
seen.
So, they are usually written as prefix.
It means that you have the function and then
you have two arguments.
Then there is infix syntax.
And that's for operators, typically things
like "1 + 2".
So, here, the "+" is an infix operator.
And you have also seen on the slides that
binary functions that would usually be written
prefix can also be written infix, if you put
them in these back-ticks `...`.
So, the "mod" is a binary function.
It can be written infix.
And now these sections.
They apply to operators/functions that are
prefix, but that we want to use in a kind
of infix style with just one of two arguments
given.
This is the "5 +" that you saw on the previous
slide.
What was this?
So, if we have a prefix function like the
"(+)", we can apply it to one of its arguments,
like 5, and then this also can be written
as this section "(5 +)" which means:
I am a function which is waiting for an argument,
then I will compute "5 plus that argument".
We also have the other way around, where we
say: Let me write the section in this way.
So, we have this binary operator (+).
And I provide one of its arguments, namely
the second one.
Then I get a function to which I can pass
a value, and then what is computed is that
value, which was passed last, plus 5.
Of course in the case of "plus" this doesn't
make a difference.
Semantically, this is of course not an interesting
difference.
We will compute the same thing, assuming that
plus (+) is commutative, which at least on
the integers, it is.
But for example, if we did this with (-), so
(5 -).
This is also possible, because (-) is a binary
operator.
And then written as (- 5), they do different
things.
Why is that?
Because one of them will wait for a value,
and then it will compute 5 minus that other
value, and the other will wait for another
value, and then compute that value minus 5.
Simply, we will apply both of these two versions
to 7, and then you will see different outcomes.
The first of these two functions applied to
7 has the result -2.
The second, applied to 7, will result in 5.
Because we could compute 7 - 5.
Why is this useful?
Is this all just somehow syntactic games that
we play?
Well, it often gives very nice, short, declarative
predicates, for example.
In this case above here, it was arithmetic
functions, but for example it is also used
for predicates and properties.
So, for example, something like '< 5' is a
function from 'Int' to 'Bool', because '<' is
an operation between two integers, 'Int' → 'Int'
→ Bool.
And if I write '(< 5)', then it is a function,
which is waiting for an argument, which could
be 3 or 7 or whatever, and will return a Boolean,
namely, whether that thing is smaller than
5.
So, if I apply the function you see here to
3, the answer will be True, because 3 is smaller
than 5.
Applying it to 7 would give False, because
7 is not smaller than 5.
So, we simply read this as "smaller than five".
It is doing exactly that.
And this is just nice syntax for that.
Let's think again about this (5 -) thing,
because this might still somehow worry you.
So, what is this (5 -)?
So, this written above is a function waiting
for an argument x and then computing 5 – x.
And the same way for all the other section
syntax cases above.
Apart from the special syntax cases using
operators, we can also just syntactically
create new functions on the fly.
So, instead of using predefined or own explicitly
defined and named functions that are already
in the program, we could also (when we want
to pass a function to another function) simply
create a new function at that point.
Such functions are called anonymous, and they
use the so-called lambda-abstraction syntax.
We have already seen this before, namely in
the context of QuickCheck tests.
There was this syntax, and I said something
like read this as a "for all", but that was
only applicable for the case of QuickCheck,
because there we want to have a predicate,
something that gave back a truth value.
And then basically the interpretation of this
predicate was that for all x the value here
should hold.
But in general, this is simply a function
which, given an x, computes something.
So, here we introduce an argument or maybe
several arguments (they can even be anonymous
again, so we could use the '_'), and then
the whole thing that we have here is in this
case a function which, given an x, computes
x + x.
And we don't give a name to this function.
So, we don't write a line "function name = some
expression".
Simply this itself is a function, which doesn't
get its own name.
In that sense, it is anonymous.
And we can use it wherever we use functions,
for example, as arguments to our 'f' from a
few slides back.
To recap, discussing this example where we
had this 'f' which expected a function from
'Int' to 'Int' and gave back an 'Int':
There are really many ways in which we can
use this.
The identity function (id) could be used for
here.
So, an existing library function could be
used as an argument.
And there are other ones that work on integers,
for example.
I just took some existing functions, or partial
applications of functions from some libraries.
Then this is something we have explicitly
discussed: that we can use operators, partially
apply them, and then get functions that could
have the appropriate type.
We can pass an anonymous function.
So, what I showed here: when we want to pass
this to f, then we have to put it in brackets
to make clear that this is the argument to
this f.
So, this goes in this place.
Then we could apply 'f' to this function.
Or, of course, with the same syntax we can
then write arbitrary expressions inside this
body, and create arbitrary anonymous functions.
And actually, this lambda-abstraction syntax
is also another point where we can get a clearer
view on Haskell's function definition syntax.
Why it is the way it is.
We talked before about these two perspectives
on the function type 'Int' → 'Int' → 'Int', seeing
it as a function of two arguments that returns
an 'Int', or seeing it as a function which takes
one 'Int' and then returns another function.
With lambda-abstraction syntax, we can actually
make this even more apparent.
Let's look at this specific case here.
Something like an 'add' function which takes
two integers and gives back an integer.
And then we can consider this to be the function
of addition, which takes two arguments and
gives back their sum.
Or, we could say: It is a function which takes
an argument x, and then returns a function;
and we can explicitly write that one as a
function which is waiting for some argument
and then returns the sum of the two.
So, for these two, we could use both these
perspectives.
This one, or the one where we have brackets
around here from a few slides back.
But they are equivalent, because these two
function definitions are equivalent.
To have a function which takes two arguments
and gives back their sum is the same as a
function which takes an argument and then
gives back a function which takes another
argument and return the sum of what has been
provided here and here.
And we could even go to further extremes and
say:
Actually, add is just something which is a
function which takes an x, and then returns
a function which takes a y, and then returns
the sum of these.
We can even move the first argument to the
right-hand side, so that we have all arguments
on the right-hand side.
And then, we can actually also shorten this
and, in lambda-abstraction syntax, directly
introduce several variables at once.
So, all these four ways are expressing the
very same thing and will be handled equivalently
by the compiler.
So, this explains, again, why we don't use
the standard mathematical notation.
Because if we had written addition as a function
like this, where we say: addition, and then
brackets where we give it two arguments separated
by a comma, then it would not have been so
clear how to express these different perspectives.
We couldn't simply move from one to the other.
But in Haskell syntax, they are all equivalent,
because they capture the same mathematical
concept of function.
This video is now getting really long.
So, now I will finish with this slide.
Now, some of you are maybe asking themselves:
Is any of that really useful to us?
Because it looked all a bit esoteric, maybe,
because I had to introduce all these different
ways of writing functions to pass to other
functions.
It was all artificial so far, except maybe
for the things that I cannot explain to you
now in inner details like "animationOf" and
"quickCheck" (the drivers of our libraries
that we have been using), which you cannot
write yourself yet, in some parts because
they interact with 'IO' (like drawing something
on screen, for example).
That is something that you don't know how
to do right now, from first principles.
So, in that sense, even though you have seen
some higher-order functions, you cannot really
write your own yet, or haven't, maybe, seen
a need for this.
Hence, so far, this might seem a bit esoteric.
But some usages would be already apparent
to you maybe now, namely for example, in the
exercise tasks where you had to draw a game
level.
Then what was the ingredient for this?
It was the 'level' function which took two
integers and gave back a code for what tile
to draw on the screen.
And this 'level' function could be seen as
data itself.
You could, for example, instead of having
it as a top-level definition, simply have
another function to which you can give a "level"
function.
And indeed, the current task from exercise
5, where there were given several depictions
of levels; that was realized by having, as
data, a list of levels, where a level is a
function.
So, we had a list of functions.
And then that was given to a drawing function
which operated on this list of functions.
So, there we had functions as data.
Again, that is something that you haven't
written yourself, but very soon, actually
in the next video, we will see more examples
of uses of higher-order.
And we will do this in the case of lists,
because there are several directly useful
higher-order functions on lists.
Less esoteric than what I have shown you in
this video, where I first wanted to get through
this basic concept of functions as arguments
to other functions and also provide certain
syntactic prerequisites.
Now, in the next video, we can use this to
do something useful on lists using higher-order
functions.